Register of the Kyril Drenikoff papers
Hoover Institution Archives
- OVERSIZE FILE, 1849-1983 (Boxes 200-214)
  - Certificates and diplomas
    - General
      - To Boris III, Czar of Bulgaria, from the Committee of the Admirers of the First Drivers of Bulgaria (on their 25th anniversary), 1937 May 22 (Folder 202: 12)
      - To Ferdinand I, Czar of Bulgaria, from the officers of the 11th regiment, 1940 September 20 (Folder 202: 13)
      - To Ferdinand I, Czar of Bulgaria, from the Deutsch-Bulgarische Freundschaft, Berlin, 1941 February 26 (Folder 202: 14)
      - To the Bulgarian National Front from Simeon II, King of Bulgaria (Folder 202: 15)
        - Undated
        - 1955 June
        - 1956 June 16
      - To Simeon II, King of Bulgaria, from Graf Dobrudjanski, Bremen, Germany, 1959 (Folder 202: 16)
    - Drenikoff, Georgi
      - High school diploma "Svidetelstvo za zrelost," Sofia, 1916 December 1 (Folder 203: 1)
      - Diploma, His Majesty's Military Academy, Sofia, (awarded in), 1917 1939 (Folder 203: 2)
      - Pilot certificate, Military Academy, Kazanlok, Bulgaria, 1929 October 25 (Folder 203: 3)
      - Certificate from Boris III, Czar of Bulgaria (Cavalry Cross with Crown), 1930 May 6 (Folder 203: 4)
      - Certificate from the Bulgarian Red Cross Society, 1934 March 8 (Folder 203: 5)
      - Certificate from Prince Paul of Yugoslavia ("Iugoslovenske Krune" order), Belgrade, 1934 (Folder 203: 6)
      - Certificates from Boris III, Czar of Bulgaria (Order of St. Alexander)
        - 1936 (Folder 203: 7)
        - 1942 (Folder 203: 8)
      - Certificate, Bulgarian Ministry of Defense (awarding Georgi Drenikoff the title of second lieutenant, in recognition of his services in World War I), 1937 June 1 (Folder 203: 9)
      - Certificate (German Service Cross), 1942 January 14 (Folder 203: 10)
      - Certificate from independent Croatia, 1942 October 7 (Folder 203: 11)
      - Certificate from the Magyarország Fömx00E9;ltóságú Kormányzója (Horthy Miklós award), Budapest, 1943 November 4 (Folder 203: 12)
    - Drenikoff, Kyril
      - High school diploma, Collège Français "S.S. Cyrille et Méthode," Sofia, 1948 (Folder 203: 13)
      - Doctorate, Université de Paris, 1959 (Folder 203: 14)
      - Diploma, Université de Paris, Institut des Hautes Etudes Internationales, 1961 (Folder 203: 15)
      - Certificate, Académie de Droit International de La Haye, 1963 (Folder 203: 16)
      - Certificate from Simeon II, King of Bulgaria (Order of St. Alexander), 1965 June 16 (Folder 203: 17)
      - Certificate, Honorifica Ordem Acadêmica São Francisco, 1967 (Folder 203: 18)
      - Certificate of participation in the 5th World Anti-Communist League (WACL) and the 17th Asian-Pacific Anti-Communist League International Conference, Manila, Philippines, 1971 July 21-26 (Folder 203: 19)
      - Certificate, Organizing Committee of 6th Conference of the World Anti-Communist League (WACL), Mexico, 1972 (Folder 203: 20)
      - Certificate of appreciation, American Council for World Freedom, host organization of the 7th Conference of the World Anti-Communist League (WACL), Washington, D.C., 1974 April 8-11 (Folder 203: 21)
      - Certificate, Legione Garibaldina, Comando Generale, 1976 (Folder 203: 22)
      - Certificate, Accademia del Mediterraneo, Rome, 1978 (Folder 203: 23)
      - Certificate, Accademia Euro-Africana, Rome, 1979 (Folder 203: 24)
      - Certificate, 13th Conference of the World Anti-Communist League (WACL), Swiss chapter, Geneva, Switzerland, 1980 July 24-27 (Folder 203: 25)
      - Miscellany (Folder 203: 26)
  - Christmas greeting addressed to Simeon II, King of Bulgaria, 1956 December (Folder 203: 27)
  - Computer portrait of Marechal Davoust, 1983 (Folder 203: 28)
  - Estimate of food prices and other products of first necessity during times of crisis and disaster, 1914 August 2 (Folder 203: 29)
  - Guest book, Simeon II, King of Bulgaria, 1965 June 16 (Folder 203: 30)
  - Itinerary for the train trip from Rovno to Vilna for Ferdinand I, Czar of Bulgaria, 1896 April 5 (Folder 203: 31)
  - Manifesto to the Bulgarian nation, signed by Ferdinand I, Czar of Bulgaria, undated (Folder 203: 32)
  - Passport given to the Belgian ship "Augustus" by the Arkhangelsk port customs, Russia, 1849 July 21 (Folder 203: 33)
  - Petitions
    - To Ferdinand I from the Saint Nicolas parish, Iskrets, Bulgaria, 1924 August 24 (Folder 203: 34)
    - To the American Government from political refugees living in the Displaced Camp, San Sabba Main, Trieste, Italy, 1957 March 25 (Map-case case)
  - Printed matter, 1859-1979 (Box 204)
    See also: SCRAPBOOKS/Atlas, 1859
    - Clippings, 1960-1979 (Boxes 205-206)
    - Magazines and newspapers, 1871-1949 (Boxes 207-211)
    - Printed reproductions of icons, paintings, and photographs (Box 212)
    - Publications related to Kyril Drenikoff's family (Box 213)
  - Program of the closure of the second session of the ordinary people's meeting, Bulgaria, 1898 February 4 (Box 214)
  - Statutes of the Order of the Holy Hungarian Crown, Budapest, 1943
  - Thank you note to Ferdinand I, Czar of Bulgaria, from the Saint Nicolas parish, Iskrets, Bulgaria, 1924 December 21 (Map-case case)
- SCRAPBOOKS, 1951-1973 (Boxes 215-218)
  Clippings, invitations, programs, and travel miscellany relating to Kyril Drenikoff's life and in particular to his trips.
  - General (clippings, invitations, programs) (Box 215)
  - Clippings, 1946-1975 (Box 216-217)
  - Travel miscellany (Box 218)
- ARTWORK, 1963-1978 (Boxes 219-228)
  Drawings and sketches, icons, printing plates, religious and watercolor paintings, arranged alphabetically by physical form.
  - Drawings and sketches (Box 219)
  - Icons
  - Printing plates (Boxes 220-224)
  - Religious paintings
    - General (Box 225)
    - On mesonite (Boxes 226-227)
  - Watercolor paintings (Box 228)
- FRAMED ITEMS, 1912-1937 (Boxes 229-239, Memorabilia cabinet)
  Icons, maps, photo portraits, and printed reproductions of icons, paintings and photographs, arranged alphabetically by physical form.
  - Decree of the Ottoman Turkish Sultan Mehmed V (in Arabic), 1912 January 22 (Box 229)
  - Map entitled "Electoratus et Palatinatus Rhem" (Memorabilia-cabinet cabinet)
  - Portraits (Box 230)
    - Ferdinand I, Czar of Bulgaria
    - Boris III, Czar of Bulgaria, alone and with his family, 1934, 1937
    - Rizov, Dimiter
  - Printed reproductions of icons, paintings, photographs, and drawings, including one of Demetrius of Bulgaria (Boxes 231-239)
- PHOTOGRAPHS, 1899-1982 (Boxes 240-260, Slide cabinet, Map case)
  989 prints, 20 albums, 16 glass and metal plates, 166 negatives, and 219 slides depicting Kyril Drenikoff, Georgi Drenikoff, the Bulgarian Royal family, the Bulgarian and German armed forces, and various aspects of Bulgarian life and history.
  - Prints
    - General
      - 2 prints depicting Kyril Drenikoff, undated (Folder 240: 1)
      - 8 prints depicting Georgi Drenikoff, undated (Folder 240: 2)
      - 1 print depicting Ferdinand I, Czar of Bulgaria, 1931 (Folder 240: 3)
      - 1 print depicting Princesses Eudoxia and Nadejda, daughters of Ferdinand I, undated (Folder 240: 4)
      - 2 prints depicting Simeon II, King of Bulgaria, undated (Folder 240: 5)
      - 72 stampsize prints depicting Simeon II, King of Bulgaria, undated (Folder 240: 6)
      - 72 stampsize prints depicting Queen Margarita, Consort of Simeon II, undated (Folder 240: 7)
      - 2 prints depicting the family of Simeon II, King of Bulgaria, undated (Folder 240: 8)
      - 1 print depicting Kyril, son of Simeon II, King of Bulgaria, undated (Folder 240: 9)
      - 22 prints depicting medals, undated (Folder 240: 10)
      - 15 prints depicting various aspects of education in Bulgaria, undated (Folder 240: 11)
      - 8 prints depicting 8 pages of Theophyla: Cti Archiepiscopi, undated (Folder 240: 12)
      - 59 prints depicting Bulgarian paintings, undated (Folder 240: 13-14)
      - 74 prints depicting Bulgarian sculptures and carvings, undated (Folder 240: 15)
      - 28 prints depicting theatrical and musical performances in Bulgaria, undated (Box-folder 241: 1)
      - 185 prints depicting Bulgarian folk art, costumes, and dances, undated (Folder 241: 2-5)
      - 15 prints depicting an exhibit of Italian books in Bulgaria, undated (Box-folder 242: 1)
      - 4 prints depicting an unknown exhibit, undated (Folder 242: 2)
      - 46 prints depicting life in Bulgaria, undated (Folder 242: 3)
      - 74 prints depicting the life of peasants in Bulgaria, undated (Folder 242: 4-5)
      - 13 prints depicting the life of workers in Bulgaria, undated (Folder 242: 6)
      - 55 prints depicting the life of Bulgarian women, undated (Folder 242: 7)
      - 1 print depicting a Bulgarian women's volleyball team, undated (Folder 242: 8)
      - 42 prints depicting urban development in Bulgaria, undated (Box-folder 243: 1)
      - 16 prints depicting Bulgarian houses and their interiors, undated (Folder 243: 2)
      - 9 prints depicting sanatoria and recreation areas in Bulgaria, undated (Folder 243: 3)
      - 20 prints depicting medical yoga diagrams, undated (Folder 243: 4)
      - 4 prints depicting ship building and ports in Bulgaria, undated (Folder 243: 5)
      - 52 prints depicting Bulgarian religious objects and 1 print depicting the Zografski monastery, undated (Folder 243: 6)
      - 1 print depicting a Communist execution in Bulgaria, undated (Folder 243: 7)
      - 1 print depicting a political poster, undated (Folder 243: 8)
      - 1 print depicting a political cartoon, undated (Folder 243: 9)
      - 2 prints depicting the Bulgarian Legation in Kiev, Ukraine, undated (Folder 243: 10)
      - 1 print depicting Joseph Stalin, undated (Folder 243: 11)
      - 1 print depicting the monument to the Soviet Army, Sofia, undated (Folder 243: 12)
    - 3 prints depicting U.S. military officers, undated (Folder 243: 13)
      - 2 prints depicting Ku Cheng-kang, undated (Folder 243: 14)
      - 1 print depicting Simeon II, King of Bulgaria, 1940 (Folder 243: 15)
      - 1 print depicting former Bulgarian officer Georgi Stoinev, 1952 (Folder 243: 16)
      - 2 prints depicting a celebration of the 10th anniversary of the Liberation of Bulgaria, Messina, Italy, 1955 (Folder 243: 17)
      - 4 prints depicting a philatelist exhibit in Bologna, Italy, 1957 (Folder 243: 18)
      - 6 prints depicting a meeting in Bologna, Italy, 1959 (Folder 243: 19)
      - 10 prints depicting Bulgarian athletes participating in the Olympic games, Rome, 1960 (Folder 243: 20)
      - 2 prints depicting members of the royal family, signed by Simeon II, King of Bulgaria, dedicated to Kyril Drenikoff, 1960-1965 (Folder 243: 21)
      - 47 unidentified prints, undated (Folder 243: 22)
    - Oversize prints
      - 1 print depicting Bulgarian contemporary life, undated (Folder 244: 1)
      - 5 prints depicting Bulgarian cultural life, undated (Folder 244: 2)
      - 4 prints depicting Bulgarian carved metal artifacts, undated (Folder 244: 3)
      - 2 prints depicting Bulgarian religious life, undated (Folder 244: 4)
      - 1 print depicting a Bulgarian contemporary office buiding, undated (Folder 244: 5)
      - 1 print depicting miners' headquarters, undated (Folder 244: 6)
      - 1 print depicting a Bulgarian port, undated (Folder 244: 7)
      - 1 print depicting Simeon II, King of Bulgaria, and his sister Maria Luisa, 1939 (Folder 244: 8)
      - 1 print depicting the 14th World Anti-Communist League (WACL) conference in Taipei, Taiwan, 1981 (Folder 244: 9)
      - 2 prints depicting the 7th and 10th World Anti-Communist League (WACL) conferences, 1974 1977 (Map-case Map case)
  - Albums
    - 7 albums of prints depicting Georgi Drenikoff, his life and military career in the Bulgarian armed forces, 1930-1943
    - 1 album of prints depicting Bulgarian and German armed forces, 1937 (Box 248)
    - 2 albums of prints depicting views of Bulgaria, 1941-1960s (Boxes 248-249)
    - 2 albums of prints depicting members of the Bulgarian royal family, 1899-1982 (Boxes 250-251)
    - 1 album of prints depicting Bulgarian archbishops, undated (Box 252)
    - 2 albums of prints depicting Bulgarian national folk art, undated (Boxes 253-254)
    - 7 albums of prints depicting World Anti-Communist League (WACL) meetings, 1974-1982 (Boxes 255-258)
  - 5 glass plates depicting people in uniform, children, an airplane, and a house, undated (Box 259)
  - 11 metal plates depicting Boris III, Czar of Bulgaria, his funeral, the Zografski monastery, stamps, and unknown people, undated
  - 166 negatives depicting Boris III, Czar of Bulgaria, his funeral, the Zografski monastery, coats of arms, buildings, maps, art of Yemen, and meetings of the World Anti-Communist League (WACL) conferences in Manila and Mexico, ,1971, 1972
  - 219 slides depicting Bulgaria, Bulgarian cities, Bulgarian icons, antique Bulgarian art, art of Thrace, and the Backovo monastery, undated (Box 260 and slide cabinet)
- POSTCARDS, 1880s-1980s (Boxes 261-265)
  Postcards depicting historical, cultural, and political centers worldwide, scenic views, art, sculpture, and architecture, including some with text.
- CARD FILE, undated (Boxes 266-269)
  Index cards listing subscribers to Edin Zavet and publications on Bulgaria.
  - Edin Zavet subscribers (Box 266)
  - Publications on Bulgaria, arranged alphabetically (Box 267-269)
- MAPS, undated (Box 270, Map case)
  Ninety-five maps of various countries in the 19th and 20th centuries, mostly Bulgaria and the Balkans.
- MEMORABILIA, undated (Boxes 271-280, Memorabilia cabinet)
  Buddha statue, buttons, cigarette lighters, coins, daggers, epaulettes, flag, ink wells, medals, military cap, Bulgarian national costume, needle work, passports, pins, plaque, sabers, sash, seals, silk scarf, stamps, and vase. Includes bust of Georgi Drenikoff.
  - Buddha statue (Box 271)
  - Buttons
  - Cigarette lighters (inscribed "The Bulgarian National Front"; "France-Bulgarie," 1958 February 19; "Macedonia for the Macedonians," William Gladstone)
  - Epaulettes (Bulgarian)
  - Flag (Bulgarian)
  - Jade piece
  - Military cap (Bulgarian)
  - Plaque
  - Sash
  - Vase
  - Coins (Bulgarian) (Box 272)
  - Passports (Bulgarian)
  - Postage stamps
  - Seals and rubber stamps (Boxes 273-275)
  - Dagger (Box 275)
  - Pins
  - Medals (Bulgarian and German) (Boxes 276-277)
    Includes a medal mounted on a wooden plaque, awarding Georgi Drenikoff the second prize in the international gliding competition in Wasserkuppe, Germany, in June 1937
  - National costume (Bulgarian) (Box 278)
  - Needlework (Bulgarian)
  - Silk scarf (Macedonian)
  - Ink wells (Box 279)
  - Plaster casts
  - Miscellany (Box 280)
    Consists mostly of Bulgarian food stuffs labels
  - Bust of Georgi Drenikoff, by Bulgarian sculptor, circa 1965 (On-shelf shelf)
  - Swords (4) (Memorabilia-cabinet cabinet)
  - Wooden stands (2) (Memorabilia-cabinet cabinet)
- MOTION PICTURE FILM, 1970, 1977, undated; 3.0 motion picture film reels (Film shelf)
  - 10th World Anti-Communist League Conference in Taipei, Taiwan, 16mm film, 1977
    Access
    Use reference ID 88009_0001_r2016.
    One color and sound reel depicting the 10th World Anti-Communist League (WACL) conference in Taipei, Taiwan, in 1977. Viewing copy available.
  - 1970 World Anti-Communist League Conference in Tokyo, Japan, 16mm film
    Use reference ID 88009_0002_r2016.
    One color and sound reel depicting the World Anti-Communist League (WACL) conference in Tokyo, Japan in 1970. Viewing copy available.
  - Untitled 16mm film reel
    One color and sound motion picture film reel depicting artworks.
- MICROFILM REEL, undated (Microfilm cabinet)
  One reel, Bibliothèque de l'Académie des Sciences, Sofia, undated.
- VIDEOCASSETTE, 1981 (Tape cabinet)
  One videocassette depicting the 14th World Anti-Communist League Conference, Taipei, Taiwan, 1981.
- SOUND CASSETTES, 1972-1979 (Cassette cabinet)
  Twenty-two sound cassettes relating mostly to Bulgarian life inside and outside the country, to Kyril Drenikoff's activities, and to international meetings.
  - Unidentified (Cassette-cabinet 1-3)
  - Bulgarian folk songs and dances, undated (Cassette-cabinet 4)
  - Family recordings entitled "Boris" and "Boyan,", undated (Cassette-cabinet 5-6)
  - Interview on Bulgarian foreign policy, undated (Cassette-cabinet 7)
  - Interview on communism in Bulgaria, undated (Cassette-cabinet 8)
  - Interview on radioactive leak in Chelyabinsk in 1957 (side 1) and Bulgarian labor camps (side 2), undated (Cassette-cabinet 9)
  - Proceedings, World Anti-Communist League (WACL) conference, Washington, D.C., undated (Cassette-cabinet 10-11)
  - Television interview, undated (Cassette-cabinet 12)
  - Speech of Kyril Drenikoff, London, 1972 (Cassette-cabinet 13)
  - Conversation, Miami, 1972 June 8 (side A); closing session, World Anti-Communist League (WACL) conference, Mexico City, 1972 August 27 (side B) (Cassette-cabinet 14)
  - Mexican folklore and magic, 1972 August 20 (Cassette-cabinet 15)
  - Christmas celebration, Food and Agriculture Organization, Rome, 1974 (Cassette-cabinet 16)
  - Bulgarian mass, 1975 (Cassette-cabinet 17)
  - French mass, 1975 (side 1); organ music (side 2) (Cassette-cabinet 18)
  - Interview of Ivan (Andy) Drenikoff, Radio Aeroporto, 1975 August (side 1); songs (side 2) (Cassette-cabinet 19)
  - Proceedings, 56th Congress of the Macedonian Patriotic Organizations in the United States and Canada, Toronto, 1977 October (Cassette-cabinet 20-21)
  - French program entitled "Qui a tué Georges Markov?,", 1979 August 24 (Cassette-cabinet 22)
- SOUND DISCS, undated (Record cabinet)
  107 sound discs of symphonic, chamber, opera and operetta music, orthodox Slavonic liturgy and songs, Bulgarian and Russian religious songs, Bulgarian folk songs, dances and music, Bulgarian modern patriotic songs, anthems, poetry reading, sermon, and children's songs.
  - Musical performances (discs 1-3), unidentified (disc 4) (Record-cabinet 1-4)
    Use copy reference numbers: 88009_a_0002984 (disc 1), 88009_a_0002986 (disc 2), and 88009_a_0002988 (disc 3)
    Disc 1 has sound recordings of musical performances. Disc 2 has sound recordings of musical performances (Side A label: John Mitsff [Mitsoff?]/Side B label: other mom). Another disc, which may be disc 3, contains a sound recording of the song "The World Will Be Free," written by John Mitsoff
  - Symphonic, chamber, opera and operetta music, performed by the Bulgarian national orchestra, a brass band, pianist Ivan Drenikoff, and Bulgarian singers (Record-cabinet 5-12)
    - Lily Ivanova and the Balkanton Orchestra performs Saturday Night, undated
      Use copy reference number: 88009_a_0001595
      Dir. Dimiter Ganeff, music Yossif Tsankoff, lyrics Dimiter Vassileff, arranged by Nicolai Arabadjieff.
    - Slav Committee of Bulgaria wishes a Happy New Year for 1971, 1970
      Use copy reference number: 88009_a_0001596
      Back label reads: "Dear fellow-countrymen and friends, The Slav Committee of Bulgaria most cordially wishes you a Happy New Year for 1971. Please accept warmest greetings and wishes for good health and prosperity from the homeland. In this festive moment, let an old patriotic song take your thoughts back to your mother country. Let the New Year be happy and successful! May it bring peace and joy to all the World's peoples!"
  - Orthodox Slavonic liturgy and songs (Record-cabinet 13-19)
  - Bulgarian and Russian religious songs (Record-cabinet 20)
  - Old Bulgarian songs (Record-cabinet 21-22)
  - Bulgarian folk songs (Record-cabinet 23-37)
  - Bulgarian folk dances (Record-cabinet 38-59)
  - Bulgarian folk music (Record-cabinet 60-67)
  - Bulgarian modern and patriotic songs (Record-cabinet 68-92)
  - Songs of Ilindensko-Preobrazhensko revolt, 1903 (Record-cabinet 93)
  - Anthems of Bulgaria, the Soviet Union, and other countries (Record-cabinet 94-95)
  - Articles of Georgi Kirkov (Record-cabinet 96)
  - Poetry reading of Khristo Botev, Ivan Vazov, and P. K. Iavorov (Record-cabinet 97-99)
  - Sermon of Patriarch Joseph I, Central Patriarch Committee of the Ukrainian Catholic Church in Great Britain, Rome, 1975 July (Record-cabinet 100)
  - Let's Join Our Hands, Friends of the Earth, children's song, undated (Record-cabinet 101)
  - Fontana di Trevi, songs by Guen Valdi, undated (Record-cabinet 102)
  - Les Cathares: Une évocation historique de Louis Double, songs and poems, undated (Record-cabinet 103)
  - Hommes et Faits du XXe siècle: Le IIIe Reich, 1849-2002 (Record-cabinet 104-107)
    Use copy reference number: 88009_a_0001714
    This is a compilation of sound recordings from 1939 to 1940. Abridged liner notes: II. - CHANTS DE GUERRE DE L'ARMEE ALLEMANDE (1939-1940); Premiere face: Adolf Hitler, Sir Neville Chamberlain, OKW, Benito Mussolini; Deuxieme face: OKW, General Huntzinger - General Keitel, Adolf Hitler, Winston Churchill.